All the meditations we're
learning are in the book. If you don't
have the book, please raise your
hand. It includes two types of meditation;
I think there are 19 meditations about
death, and we're going to learn
those. There's a part about the Meditations of
Death,
and at the end, you'll see some meditations
by
Camila. All the Impressions
and those meditations by Cala, we're going to
do this
afternoon and
tomorrow. Using
photographs, you can remember the
meditation. You remember the photo.
So, I'm going to ask you to study the
photographs, and you can remember them
when you're in the middle of the
meditation. You can bring the photograph to
your
mind. So, what's the first
photograph? Someone doing
yoga, two women practicing yoga,
very
healthy. Sometimes strong,
healthy people die in a car accident
minutes later, and then they're in another
world minutes later. "
Haar" in the
book means not to be
depressed, not to be
sad, to be happy. It
means that if you think about your
death, you're not going to waste your
time, and you're going to enjoy your
life. I don't have to tell you that you're going to
die; you
know it, but your whole life you're kind of
avoiding thinking about it,
and in the tradition of
Tonapa, we embrace our
death. We don't say no, no, no, I'm not going to
die. We say yes, I'm going to
die. Maybe I'm going to die during
yoga class. Deita, I was once very
close.
It's better if you admit it's
possible, and then you can enjoy your
life and not waste your
time. The purpose of death meditations is
not some dark, weird thing.
If you do a good
death meditation, you will be very
happy because you are using your life in
the best
way. It takes a lot of effort to be
avoiding death and pretending you're
not going to
die. It's better to be honest.
With vitamins, my yoga, and my
green juice, I could die in 5
minutes. My doctor makes me take
like 50 kinds of
vitamins
because he wants me to be
healthy, and he also
sells them to me. So when I see that bottle of
vitamins on my
table, it's 30 pills a month. How many will I
finish before I
die? Maybe there will be 20 left when I
go. So everything
around us is telling us about
our
death. Just the vitamins there on our
table. How many can I finish
before I
die? The rest of the
vitamins...
When you see things in your
home...  Think about it,
and it's not sad. It
helps you live a happier and
deeper life. And maintaining that thought of
avoiding death is
foolish. It requires a lot of
work. This class lasts for a week, 10
days. We are going to learn to embrace
death
because we want to
conquer it. We learn to
embrace it. It's a
Sanskrit word. It means
death. It means time,
which is the wheel of
time. "Ca" means the time of your life.
Your death. "D
meck danda" means a
stick. We are going to shovel death. We are going to
kill it. As the other way in Sanskrit is to
say, to put, to
kill
death. "Llama" means
death. "Anta" means to
finish. It means terminator.
The purpose of this
class is to become familiar with
death. Let it come near,
and then
give it to it. You don't have to
die. That is one of the purposes of
this
class: to learn not to
die. But to learn
that, you have to learn how to
die. So this
week we are going to think about
death, talk about
it, bring it
near, and then kill it.
We are going to start with the
book. I always put the pictures on the
projector, and you can see the
Tibetan, but you don't have to worry
if you are not interested in the Tibetan. I don't care.
100,000 books in Tibetan about
how to kill
death in English. There are 100,000
silly novels, but I think you should
learn
Tibetan even if you don't want to. I'm
going to talk about
Tibetan every
day, and I'm going to plant a seed in your
mind, and by accident, you'll learn
Tibetan. So relax and open your
mind.
My teacher taught me this book for almost 30
years, and we went over it three
times. It's called Enlightenment from A to
Z: The Fool's Guide to
Enlightenment.
If you just sit here in this
class and
come to as many retreats as you
can, you'll become
enlightened. You'll get
there. It's fun being a
Buddha. If you help one old lady, you
feel happy.
You can help a billion old ladies
at the same
time, and you'll feel
happy. So this book tells you
how. This was written by
my
teacher's teacher, and I promised to finish this book. We've already
finished almost 400
pages. So we have 600
pages left. We've already done 22 retreats to
get
here. That's like more retreats
to finish.  If you
finish, I don't care if only one
person comes, if no one comes, I'll keep doing
it. But if you want to conquer
death, you have to
come. If you don't have money, just talk to
us, we'll sort it out. It's
not about
money, it's about conquering
death. It's
free. The room has a price, but
we can fix it.
Who's translating? Do
n't worry about the Tibetan, just
open your minds and laugh.
I want to speak in Tibetan because
I want to plant a seed in your minds. I'm
going to quote a Lama
called the First Panch
Lama. He lived about 400
years ago. They spend their whole lives taking care
of their
bodies with great
love. He has to come and teach this
morning,
and he has a
pimple, and he's like, "Oh, I have to
squeeze it." That's how we take care of our bodies
for many
years. But when the time comes to
die, this body... I drink and drink liquids.
Andreana makes my
juices.
Secret coffee—we don't tell her.
And I try to find some hair to
comb. I make sure all my clothes are
neatly
arranged. I do
yoga. Maybe people will
notice and take care of their
bodies.  They spend a lot of time with their
body, but the day they
die, light means he's going to
betray them. They took care of him all their life, and
then it's like, "
Goodbye." But wait, I took care of you all my life. No, I'm
leaving. I found another guy or a woman. I don't need you. No, no, I'm leaving. No, no, they can't trust him. He's like
a bad
husband. They can't trust
him. He'll leave them.
All the time they
dedicated to him, he's going to leave them.
We have to think about it.
In fact, it's the last meditation of the
19 meditations on death. You
can check number
19. What is he doing? He
found a pimple and he's combing his hair.
That's the last meditation on
death that we're going to
do, maybe in three or four days.
These are all the meditations I
taught you at the
last retreat, so you're missing the ones from the last
retreat, and
this is so that you remember the
meditations on
death. So you have to think about
the three
reasons.
What is the third principal reason? There are
three
reasons. So these are the
nine traditional meditations on
death. The third
is  When you
die, nothing will
help you except these
classes, your
meditation, and the goodness of helping
others.
There are three
reasons why. Number
one: everything you worked for to acquire
things can't help you.
Nothing—car, house,
family,
job, name,
yoga—nothing
helps. Only
dharma, what's in your
heart, will help you when you die.
The rest won't. It doesn't
mean you have to
sell your car
today.
You can have a nice car; you're
not going to die. Have a
nice car. It's not wrong to have good
things; it's
good, but you have to have your dharma
ready.
Also, a good
car, a nice house,
a nice family,
good dharma—
have both. Everything is
fine. If you don't have a car, if you don't have
a house, it's difficult to do
dharma. Have both.
Okay, this prayer is very
important. Oh, excuse me.
First reason: money can't
help you at that
moment. Number two: your family, your friends
can't
help you. They can hold your
hand, say, "Please don't die, we
love you." You're going to get cold, and they're going to say, "
Like
family and friends, we
love you." Having a nice family and
great
friends is fine. Even the Mexican baby epidemic
is fine,
fine, but you have to be ready because even
those children...  They can
help you, and they go alone; nobody can
help them. That's why we think of our Lama in
each meditation,
because when you
die, the Lama can help you and
guide you to where to
go. The
third thing is that even your body can't
help you; your body will deceive you like a
bad
husband. It will leave.
Now, a very, very
important prayer after you meditated
on those three
things: money can't
help me, my friends can't help me,
my own body can't
help me. After you meditated on
those three things, it does
n't help to get
depressed. It's very important when
you teach this to your own
students: don't let them get depressed and
say, "Oh, I'm going to commit
suicide." The end isn't to say, "I'm
not going to bathe anymore, I'm going to
die." It's like this: do
n't get
sad. And this prayer is very
important: it doesn't help to get
sad. You have to drink
soda about your
breasts, as well as... Don't get depressed
alone.
You're going on a
long trip. At DCI, we have a
rule, and none of us follow the
rule: 48 hours before the DCI tour,
your suitcase is ready.
So you don't go crazy at the last
minute. Your suitcase...  Death has to
be
ready, Ponz, have your death bag ready
here. Last minute, you're not going to be like this,
crazy. Pack it now and then relax,
okay?
If your bag is ready, you can live, you can
enjoy your
life. The night before the DCI tour,
you can go to
dinner because your bag is
ready and you can enjoy.
This is a
famous Lama, it's like
Guadalajara, it means like Mr.
Guadalajara, lived
1762-1823.
If you don't know where you're going
after you
die, the Dharma will
help you. Your Lama will
help you after you
die. They have the power to
help you, they can teach you. Go, go
left, go right, no, don't go that way. It
means
like provisions for the journey,
provisions for the
journey, protein bars.
The rule says there are numbers.
Always eat
protein bars, you never know what food they'll give you
in Kazan.
The protein bars mean the
Dharma. Have your Dharma ready.
When things get tough on
your Dharma
journey, Dharma will
help you like a
policeman. If something bad happens during your
journey, Dharma will
help you. And come to as
many Dharma events as you
can so you do
n't have to come to Dharma classes.
Excuses for not doing your other
things. I'm sorry, I can't go to the movies with
you. I have to do my meditation
about death. It
's
Milare, the most famous meditator in
Tibet. He lived about 800
years ago. He wrote very beautiful poetry.
That
poetry is good for us because he
started his retreats when he was 50.
So don't tell me you're already
old. The person who did the most
famous retreats in Tibet started doing retreats
until he was
50. And this is in a country where the
life expectancy was 40. He
had a
Tibetan student wife. They
say their
names are very
close and very much so.
You are rich, but you also have diabetes.
The path of this life is long,
but the path after life is even
longer. Are you ready?
If you're not
ready, then you should share what
you have with other
people.
So he's telling us how to have
our suitcase
packed. If you have
money, if you have a house. I really
like the German group. When
the refugees from
Syria arrived, they took some in. Some are
living at Silvia's house.
So Silvia's suitcase is
packed. It's not easy to take someone into your
home,
feed them,
take care of them, but if you want to have your suitcase packed,
that's right.  As you should have
ready, share what you have with other
people. We always have something to
share, my beloved disciple.
This life is something that
frightens me. When I see baby K, the little one,
when I see him I say, "Oh, you're going to steal
many things in your life,
many things that are frightening in this
life." But you still don't see
anything. After death is much more
frightening. If you think this is
scary, wait until after you die.
This world is nothing compared to the
next
world. Is your suitcase
ready? If you don't have your suitcase
ready, then something about
the person who will guide us after
death comes from the
DMA. The person who will help us when we
are in
trouble is putting a refugee in your
house.
What you are going to eat on that
journey comes from sharing with other
people. It
means having a
house and there is a fence
around it, like in Guadalajara we have
these high walls.
Where is the
grass? It means a dirty old dog,
not like Cindura, your cat, but an
ugly old dog. It
means the one you use to
talk to your teacher or a monk.
Come, but it is a great
insult. "Dirty old dog"
is a very famous word that you
should learn.
When people learn another language, they
always learn  The first bad words, the
fastest bad words,
my Lama's nephew stayed
with
us. My Lama told me, "Teach him
English." I tried for almost two
years with my
Lama and I said, "It's impossible, he can't
learn
English." And he said, "If he can't learn
English, he has to get a
job." And he got a job in
a
hamburger restaurant washing plates
and he burned his hand and I said, "Damn, don't say that, it's
a bad
word." And he said, "It's not a bad
word, you know what it means." "
Who told you that?
Nobody taught me." When the
cook burns his hand, he always says, "Oh,
in Tibet, if you want to say
a bad word to
someone, you can say, 'It
means
old.' It means that an old dog has long
hair
here. Dogs here have long hair,
but in
Tibet they refer to someone who doesn't know
anything, someone stupid.
You're going to die like an
old dog. An old dog doesn't
prepare, they didn't learn to pack their
suitcase, and you're going to be the same,
run over on the
road, or you're going to die with
style. Don't die like an old dog,
die with
style. Let's say another prayer and
let's do a Med. I
did the morning teaching.  It was too
long because people were still
awake. I made the afternoon lesson
shorter because people always fall
asleep. Some people learn better
when they're asleep. I do
n't know about your room, but in my room,
half the things don't work.
None of the lights work.
The water keeps running from the tap; it does
n't
stop. And last night, during the
emergency time, the toilet didn't work.
And to tell you the truth, I don't care. I'm
not going to
fix it.
Because
after 10
days, I'm not going to go to Walmart and buy
everything it needs and
fix it. That's what it says
here: guests don't fix things
in the
house. What does that mean? No, don't
waste your life fixing things you're
not going to see. You're going to die; you're going to move on.
So when your husband says, "I'm not
going to fix that in the house," he's right. We're
not going to be here long enough
to fix it. For the
children, you have to let them
fix it.
People who are going on trips don't
fix their toilets; they don't fix the
candy. They just pack their
suitcases. My suitcase is packed.
Everything is ready. The next place we're
going to is our next destination. I
'm ready
for Singapore. I'm ready for
Singapore.  I packed my suitcase. I don't
care about the lights or the toilet
here. I already have my suitcase
ready. So you should make a
decision. I'm
not going to worry about things that will be
lost in a few
years. It doesn't mean you shouldn't
fix the toilet in your
house. It means pack your suitcase
first and then fix your
toilet. Then you can relax at
home.
When I woke up, I packed my
suitcase. Then I had a great
yoga class, and we had a great
meditation, and we had an
amazing breakfast. But if my suitcase isn't
ready, I have to prepare. I have to
worry about it.
If the suitcase is ready, I can enjoy
breakfast. If your dharma is
ready, you're ready to
die, and then you can really enjoy
your
life
without guilt, without
guilt. You're just
ready. So the doctor tells you, "You have
cancer." Okay, I'm
ready. Okay,
pack your
suitcase, and then you can enjoy your
life. Where will you go after you
die? Oh, I see. I've fixed it. I've been
meditating
a lot, and I've
prepared it. I know where I'm going.
I have an idea about the
homework. It's going to
help me. What I'd like to do is that
every day I'm going to give you a
homework question
on your
phone. This is coming.  From China
mainly, so the homework for
today is to start a
chat group. You can help with that,
and we're all going to need the
app. It's going to be like the
Chapala Retreat group, the Chapala Retreat group. I
want you to send a
text describing something in your home.
I'll give an
example: when my father got cancer, he had
a very strong
lung cancer and couldn't eat
food. So I had to make him
fresh
orange juice. For a couple of weeks, he lived on only
orange juice. So when someone makes me
orange juice, I
see it. I really like
orange juice, but I always think of my
father, and it reminds me of my own
death and things like that.
Send a text
about something in your
home that reminds you of
death in a positive way, not
depressing like now. When I take
vitamins, I think about the rest of the
vitamins. That's
the thing in my
house. Spanish, English,
Russian—the
best ones you can put on
Facebook, and the very best one will
be on my
Facebook. Any language is fine, your
own
language. Hopefully, you can have one for the class.
Every day it's going to be a
different one. It's your homework. It's a
modern homework assignment. It took me a long time to come up
with this.  The
idea for the evening and
afternoon classes is to have music
or read something you like
and share it with
us before
class. So if you have any music you
want to
play, a
poem—the group from China sang together,
about 10 people—
anything you want to
do, talk to us. Do
n't wait until
Friday because everyone waits until
Friday and we don't have time for everyone.
After that, just talk.
There, stand up.
Let's do a little more of the text,
and Nicole has to keep the list of
who did their homework and who did
n't. If you do your WeChat homework, they're going to
give you a certificate at the end of the
course, and then you can share the course
with other
people. If you don't do the homework, they're not going
to give you a certificate
or fix
that. Traditional aspects of
death in the
book. But we're going to continue doing those
meditations during the
week. The next part in this
book means practicing what it would
feel like to die. This is
n't part of the traditional old books
of the master; in a
way, it's like having the real
feeling of that subject, like what it
really feels like to
die. It's easier to have your bag packed
if you know what's coming,
what the weather is like there, if there will be mosquitoes.  I'm
asking you these
questions. Should I pack a
sweater? Will I need an
umbrella? We need to talk about
that. There are some traditional Tibetan teachings
and prayers
to prepare for
dying, and what you should
pack. The name of the book is called You
Are My Compassionate Protector. It
means, "You will save me from going to a bad
place after I
die." And we're going to have two
special classes this
week. What days
are on the path of
preparation? And I'm going to teach you. There's a
special guarantee you can get
that if you die
suddenly or
slowly, you don't have to go to a
bad place. We're going to have two classes about
that. What
days? Monday is the
first one, and
Saturday we're going to have a special class
about
that. There's another
book,
by Synapse. It was very
good. He wrote a book called Tang. It
means the place, the place between
death and rebirth, the place of the
Spirits, the Spirit Realm.
People call it the
Bardo. Between death and
rebirth, Tang means I live on a
plateau on a mountain,
and then there's a
ravine down below. Down below the ravine, there's
a
small river. You can swim in that
stream. You just have to stretch out, you have to
lie very
flat, and your stomach will...  scrape
on the
stones sometimes  I like going down there, I
can take off my clothes, and I can't
jump, I crawl to the
water, but there's no path to go down the
canyon. But I found the
Deer Trail; it's very narrow, you have to
be very careful because it's
very
slippery. And if you fall, well, you
fall. I have a friend who climbed Mount
Everest; the last 10 meters, like Hillary Pass,
is that
narrow, and it's
ice, and you can't use ropes, they won't
help you. You have to balance; you
can't use the last 10 meters to
get to the bottom. If you fall on this side,
you fall 2,000
meters; if you fall on the other side, you fall
3,000 meters.
Nobody can help you, and you have to go
alone. And the last 10 meters are like that.
That's a
Tibetan saying: when you
die, in the
Spirit World, you're on a very narrow,
dangerous path, and that's called
a very narrow, dangerous path between
death and
rebirth. Because if your suitcase isn't
completely
prepared, you're going to fall. You have to be
very
careful. It means
like
free; the name of the book is that you are
free from that.  Narrow and dangerous path
between death and rebirth,
and that book teaches you how to be safe during
that
time. There's another book with the same
name; people translate it as the
Tibetan Book of
Death, and in
many
English it's called the Tibetan Book of
Death. That's a
mistake; forget it, do
n't waste your
time. A classmate at the
monastery studied that
book, and
he's crazy. Forget that
book. This one is
better than what I heard this
week.
That book was written by the First Panchen Lama.
So let's learn that
together. You have to
think: sooner or later I will
die. You have to think, 'It's going to happen to me.'
And here are some tips from the book
by the First Panchen
Lama. The doctor tells your family, 'That's all I
can
do.' My dad's doctor told me, '
Take him
home, let him die at home.'
And we said, 'When are you
coming?' The doctor said, 'I don't have to
go now. It's not in my
hands anymore.' It means you can call
all the Lamas, all the priests,
but it's too late. There's nothing there,
nothing to be done.'
Then your whole
family decides, 'Well, that's it, he's going to
die.'  My father had
very
expensive surgery. They broke all the bones in his
back and opened him up
like this and cut out some
lung cancer. Then they saw it and said, "No, no, just sew it back up, it's
too late."
And your family loses hope
and you're left wondering, "What's going to happen to me
now?" Remembering
my
teacher's words is the only thing that will
help you in that
time. Anything you heard in
this class will
help you. I
hope I remember something
my Lama told me. Not a fight I had with
my
girlfriend. You reach a point where your
illness, sir,
and the
doctor
try to understand. It means to
argue. It's a number
where the doctor starts talking about two
different things. What are they? To the
patient, he says, "Don't worry, it
seems you're going to get
better." Then he tells the family, "
Prepare yourselves, he's going to die in about three days."
The doctor splits his words in two, divides them
in
two. Then your family and
friends arrive at your bedside.
You understand the word because you know the
word, not obvious,
hidden. This is a good example of the
word used in a  Real-life case.
So Adam can add it to the
dictionary. We're making a
dictionary, a video
dictionary. Sometimes I'm going to stop and
explain. The word is for a
video
dictionary. "As"
means privately, that they do it. "
Elar"
can also mean the
inside of the body, the
chest. It means where you can't
see it. "Con aspira" means inside. "Ch" you
can
hear. In the study of perception, in
Buddhism and
logic, it means things you can't
see, like
something happens to you.
Your boyfriend breaks up with
you. If you're
Buddhist and you
studied it, you know
why. It's because you didn't keep your
promises. You can't see what happened, but you
understand it from your logic: I should have
broken my
promises. That means it's not something you
can see, it's not something you
can
hear, but it's something you can make
a logical deduction about. "
Finally," dictionary: you ca
n't
hear. They start wrapping, wrapping,
packing your life and your
things. Let's start another
dictionary entry. It means to clean your
room.
If you say "your room," it
means clean your
room. What does it mean?
Here they are already packing your life, your
things.
Who am I going to give this
table to? Where are their account numbers? Does
anyone have their
account numbers? Who's going to stay?  With the car,
this is when the family starts
fighting. It's very common for the family to
start
fighting. They've already decided you're going to die.
Sometimes the person doesn't cooperate and doesn't
die for the next two
years. Then
slowly, when you
die, the warmth of your
body, the tips of your fingers get
cold first,
and your toes too,
and slowly the cold rises, like this,
and you can
feel it. The cold starts in your fingers and
starts to rise, like this, and
then you know you're going to
die.
Breath means breath
meditation. It
means you start having
trouble
breathing. You can snort
as if you don't get enough
exercise and are always like this.
In Tibetan, it sounds like the word
for eating, but it's not the
correct grammar.
It means the pores of your nose
start to
shrink. Your lips start to twist, like this. It
means that you lose your pink
complexion. You start to
lose many ugly, unpleasant things.
They start to happen outside and
inside, and you start to remember all
the things you did to hurt
others,
and you start to regret all the
bad things you did to them.
So, if we're all going to
die, the people who hurt you the
most in your
life—I don't know, were you married for 20 years
or 10 years,
ugly—let it go, let it
go
now. Don't hold on to any of
it, don't hold on to even
10%. It's not for the bad guy, it's
for
you. Just forget, forgive, pardon,
hate, or that
anger. Someone
hurt you, someone stole
something from you, someone left you for another
woman. Immediately
forgive, let it go. Just
kidding. It doesn't mean he didn't do something
wrong. They did something very bad,
and it's true that they
hurt you, and it's true that it was very bad
karma. But karma will take care of that.
You don't have to
worry about it. From your
side, let it go
now because when you're lying down
and
dying, it's going to hurt you. So let it go
now. I hope you
live a
happy life. I hope you like your new
girlfriend. I hope you have a very nice time. I
forgive you
100%. Just let it
go because when you're
dying, all those things are going to come back to haunt
you.  They wouldn't let go. They wouldn't let
go,
and they're going to make a very
dangerous path. Let him
go, and you can die in
peace. And we don't know when we're going to die.
So let him go
now. We all have a tragic story
about someone doing
something to us. If you take it to your deathbed, it's going to
be very dangerous in the
bardo. So let him
go, not because you're
compassionate, because I don't want to die like that.
I don't want to have a bad death. I
hate you. You
did something very stupid to me, wrong, and I
forgive you. I don't want to carry that to the
bardo. So let him
go. It doesn't mean you're not a bad
person. You are a bad person, but
let him go. They're going. I'm
dying today. I'm
free. If you keep thinking about that guy
when you're going to die, you should
think about that again.
So it should be. No, no, no, I don't
want
that. Let him go.
Let's stop here. Shh, shh. Adam, we're
in